בוקר
טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is ז, Zayin, סנהדרין Sanhedrin 7,
but we are behind, so we pick up at the bottom of
very bottom of ו עמוד א, vav amud alef, 6A, and we
are אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, three, four lines from the
bottom, so we were just going through a whole discussion about פשרה
pshara versus דין, din, compromise versus judgment, and whether you need
like three or one or maybe even two, but two really
was less about to make the פשרה pshara effective but to make
be witnesses, but whether פשרה pshara is a type of a דין,
din, binding arbitration is a type of a empowering people to render
judgment or whether it's type of just a contractual agreement depends on
whether you need three fundamentally or one. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, אמר רב אשי שמע מינה פשרה אינה צריכה קניין.
Amar Rav Ashi shman mina pshara eina tzricha kinyan. From this debate
of three versus one, we can infer that compromise, פשרה, pshara, binding
arbitration, does not need a קניין, kinyan, does not need somebody to
do a קניין סודר, kinyan sudar, you know, to do the handkerchief
thing to say that they're obligating themselves to the decision. Why? How
do you infer that? דאי סלקא דעתך צריכה קניין, Di salka daitach
tzricha kinyan, because were you to say that it would require that,
then למאן דאמר תלתא למה לי תסגי בתרי ולקני מיניה. l'man de'amar
tlata lama li tiskei bitrei v'likni minei. So what would be the
logic of three? Then if you're doing a קניין, kinyan, then you're
actually obligating yourself based on what the decision would be and therefore,
you know, two should be enough, you know, two to be witnesses,
there's a whole question whether קניין kinyan you need עדים edim or
not, you know, to create a binding obligation through a קניין, kinyan,
but you certainly should not need three, you're just obligating yourself based
on what this person decides. So since there's an opinion that you
need three, clearly we're operating in a mechanism that's not just about
imposing an obligation on yourself, a type of a contractual obligation, because
if we were, and you did a קניין kinyan to make that
binding, then nobody would say that three would be necessary. So that
seems to be a, you know, a pretty reasonable point.
But then the גמרא Gemara surprisingly concludes and says the following,
ולקני מיניה. v'likni minei. So why not just so if it need
so if תלתא למה לי תסגי בתרי ולקני מיניה, tlata lama li
tiskei bitrei v'likni minei, so if it was just if you did
a קניין kinyan who would need three, just do a קניין kinyan
and you have עדים, edim, right, there should be no need for
three, והלכתא, v'hilchata, but the הלכה halacha is פשרה צריכה קניין, pshara
tzricha kinyan, that actually פשרה pshara does need קניין, kinyan, presumably, you
know, even if you actually require three.
And or now if or depending one or three, but the debate
of one or three exists assuming that a קניין kinyan is taking
place. Now it makes sense that you need a קניין kinyan because
you need to make a binding agreement that you're committing yourself to
the agreement that's going to come out with, you know, that that
the either the panel or the individual will decide. So it's understandable
why you need a קניין kinyan to make it binding, but then
what do you do with the argument of well once that's true,
then who needs three? Then you've just made it binding whatever somebody
says. So if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot
says והלכתא פשרה צריכה קניין והא דלא סגי בתרי משום דהוי כקניין
בטעות דלא בקי בפשרה שפיר, v'hilchata pshara tzricha kinyan v'ha d'lo sagi
bitrei mishum d'havei k'kinyan b'ta'us d'lo b'ki b'pshara shapir, that the reason
you would need three would be because at the end of the
day, you know, it's not like you're going to agree to something
that's going to be a roll of the dice, you know, then
you get into like questions about אסמכתא. asmachta. You're agreeing to something
that is a legitimate compromise
decision and therefore the argument would be that even though you're saying
you're agreeing to it, if it's any less than three, we would
be concerned that that would actually be a, you know, a non-responsible
decision and a non, you know, legitimate type of a decision that
the panel would arrive at. So you're because you're not committing yourself
to the arbitrary words that come out of the mouth of the
panel but to a legitimate type of a פשרה. pshara. Okay, and
so that's why you can demand three even if you're even if
it has a קניין. kinyan. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this, תנו רבנן כשם שהדין בשלושה כך ביצוע בשלושה. tanu rabbanan
k'shem she'adin b'shlosha kach bitzua b'shlosha. Okay, so this is the idea
that פשרה pshara or ביצוע bitzua depending on the phrase you want
needs three just like דין din so it is type of a
rendering of a decision. נגמר הדין אי אתה רשאי לבצוע. Nigmar hadin
i ata rasha l'vto'a. However, once they actually the court has, you
know, come to the conclusion and we'll see if you look at
רש"י, Rashi, the גמרא Gemara will say it later, שאמרו איש פלוני
אתה זכאי איש פלוני אתה חייב, she'amru ish ploni ata zakai ish
ploni ata chayav, they actually say you're liable,
you're exempt, that is called גמר דין, gmar din, then you can't
say oh wait, I want to make a compromise. Now why the
other side would agree to a compromise who even knows, okay, but
clearly once the judgment is rendered you can no longer ask for
compromise, that becomes binding. All right, רבי אליעזר בנו של רבי יוסי
הגלילי אומר. Rabbi Eliezer beno shel Rabbi Yossi HaGlili omer. Now we're
going to get into different opinions about whether compromise is a good
idea or not a good idea, you know, and it's a sort
of a tension between אמת emet and שלום, shalom, דין. din. might
be the most true conclusion according to the law, maybe even according
to justice, but it doesn't necessarily make all parties
happy and people could still wind up feeling cheated even if technically
from a legal perspective and feel that it wasn't fair and a
lot of other things and maybe even justly so. So פשרה pshara
hopefully tries to achieve more of a sense of שלום shalom and
making everybody okay with the final decision, but maybe to some degree
at the cost of אמת. emet. So there's going to be a
question which of these is to be preferred and at some level
the also the issue is sort of at which stage of the
conversation. So let's take a look. רבי אלעזר בנו של רבי יוסי
הגלילי אומר, Rabbi Eliezer beno shel Rabbi Yose HaGlili omer, אסור לבצוע,
assur livtzoa, you it is forbidden to compromise and come to some
type of binding arbitration. וכל הבוצע הרי זה חוטא, vechol habotzeia harei
zeh chotei, and if you do it you're sinning because you're perverting
truth. וכל המברך את הבוצע, vechol hamevarech et habotzeia, anybody who gives
a blessing, oh look at them, he managed to work out a
good compromise, הרי זה מנאץ, harei zeh mena'etz, you're actually, you know,
you're cursing God, you're blaspheming. ועל זה נאמר בוצע ברך ניאץ ה׳,
ve'al zeh ne'emar botzeia bereich ni'etz Hashem, and the בוצע botzeia who
blesses, you know, that might mean the one who like ill-gotten gains
might be the פשט pshat of the פסוק, pasuk, but here we're
reading it that the one who makes a compromise and who blesses
the one who made the compromise is blaspheming God. אלא יקוב הדין
את ההר, ela yikov hadin et hahar, the judgment has to pierce
the mountain, no matter how big the obstacle you have to stay
true to the true justice and that can never be compromised.
Okay, שנאמר, shene'emar, the verse says כי המשפט לאלוקים הוא, ki hamishpat
lelokim hu, and that's why you are, it's like you're blaspheming God.
God is entrusted you to instill justice in this world and therefore
you have to be true to the law even if it makes
some people upset. All right, וכן משה היה אומר, vechen Moshe haya
omer, and this is משה Moshe is going to be contrasted to
אהרן. Aharon. אהרן Aharon was, you know, the רודף שלום rodef shalom
and אוהב שלום ohev shalom and so on and משה Moshe was
very much like the stern justice, you know, coming down from הר
סיני Har Sinai God's law. וכן משה היה אומר יקוב הדין את
ההר. vechen Moshe haya omer yikov hadin et hahar. אבל אהרן, aval
Aharon, ואהרן, ve'Aharon, אוהב שלום ורודף שלום, ohev shalom verodef shalom, loved
peace, ran after it, ומשים שלום בין אדם לחברו, umesim shalom bein
adam lechavero, and made peace between one person and his friend. שנאמר,
shene'emar, the verse says תורת אמת הייתה פיהו ועוולה לא נמצא בשפתיו,
torat emet hayta bepihu ve'avla lo nimtza bisfatav, a teaching of truth
was on his mouth and perversion was not found on his lips.
בשלום ובמישור הלך איתי, beshalom uvemishor halach iti, with peace and with
like
righteousness, the straight path he walked with me, ורבים השיב מעוון, verabim
heshiv me'avon, and many he turned away from sin. Now of course
that sounds all very nice. Okay, and we know that it's talking
about אהרן Aharon if you see רש״י Rashi because it says the
beginning of the פסוק pasuk is כי שפתי כהן ישמרו דעת, ki
siftei kohen yishmeru da'at, because, you know, the word, the lips of
a כהן kohen will keep the,
you know, knowledge. So teaching. So anyway, but the question is this
seems very praiseworthy of אהרן Aharon but you just said אסור לבצוע.
assur livtzoa. So if you look at רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi says
like this. אסור לבצוע, assur livtzoa, the top second line from רש״י,
Rashi, מי שבאו לדין אסור לדיינים לבצוע. mi shebau ledin assur ladayanim
livtzoa. Once it's coming to the judges, once they've presented yourself in
a court and they've come to the place of justice you have
to instill justice. אבל אהרן, aval Aharon, what אהרן Aharon did was
to make peace before they were seeking justice. And if you look
at the next one, אבל אהרן אוהב שלום ורודף שלום, aval Aharon
ohev shalom verodef shalom, רש״י Rashi says וכיון שהיה שומע מחלוקת ביניהם
קודם שיבואו לפניו לדין היה רודף אחריהם ומטיל שלום ביניהם. vekeivan shehaya
shomeia machloket beineihem kodem sheyavou lefanav ledin haya rodef achareihem umetil shalom
beineihem. Before they would seek justice. So you always can try to
seek peace first, but once you come to seek justice you can't
pervert justice and try to come up with some type of a
compromise. That is the position of רבי אליעזר בנו של רבי יוסי
הגלילי. Rabbi Eliezer beno shel Rabbi Yose HaGlili. Okay. Now, רבי אליעזר
אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, now that we quoted this פסוק pasuk about
בוצע ברך botzeia bereich we're going to digress a little. רבי אליעזר
אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, הרי שגזל סאה של חיטים וטחנה ואפאה, harei
shegazal se'ah shel chitim utchanah ve'afah,
somebody stole a, you know, a pound of flour of grain and
he ground it and he baked it, והפריש ממנה חלה, vehefrish mimena
challah, and separated חלה. challah. כיצד מברך, keitzad mevarech,
how could this person make a ברכה? bracha? The question is ברכה
bracha on the הפרשת חלה, hafrashat challah, ברכה bracha on המוציא, hamotzi,
it's debated in the פוסקים, poskim, but anyway, אין זה מברך אלא
מנאץ, ein zeh mevarech ela mena'etz,
this would not be a blessing, this would be a blasphemy. It's
like מצווה הבאה בעבירה, mitzvah haba'ah be'aveirah, using the sin and now
thinking that you're going to bring it and bless God over this
thing that is stolen. ועל זה נאמר ובוצע ברך ניאץ ה׳, ve'al
zeh ne'emar ubotzeia bereich ni'etz Hashem,
the one who breaks the loaf of bread, that's how we're reading
בוצע botzeia now, and gives a blessing is cursing God. רבי מאיר
אומר, Rabbi Meir omer, לא נאמר בוצע אלא כנגד יהודה. lo ne'emar
botzeia ela keneged Yehuda. This idea of being a בוצע botzeia is
said about יהודה, Yehuda, שנאמר, shene'emar,
we just had this actually last week's פרשה, parsha, ויאמר יהודה אל
אחיו מה בצע כי נהרוג את אחינו וכיסינו את דמו, vayoimer Yehuda
el achav mah betza ki naharog et achinu vechisinu et damo, you
know, what good will it be that we will kill our brother
and cover up his blood? Let's sell him to the Ishmaelites and
they sold him and that brought יוסף Yosef all the way down
to Egypt. So somebody said, oh look how great יהודה Yehuda is,
he managed to save יוסף Yosef from the pit. So, you know,
what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is saying is are you kidding? He
was in a position that he could have convinced them to
return. Alright if you bless him then that is blaspheming God you
need to talk about what he
really could have
done וכל המברך את יהודה הרי זה מנאץ vechol hamevarech es Yehuda
harei ze mena'etz and if you bless him you're blaspheming and על
זה נאמר ובוצע ברך ניאץ ה'. ve'al ze ne'emar uvotzea berech ni'etz
Hashem. רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha says מצוה לבצוע.
mitzvah livtzoa.
Now back to our main
point. Okay rather than saying it's אסור לבצוע assur livtzoa he's saying
it's a מצוה mitzvah presumably even after they have come to the
בית דין. beis din. So מצוה לבצוע mitzvah livtzoa שנאמר אמת ומשפט
שלום שפטו בשעריכם. shenemar emes umishpat shalom shiftu besha'areichem. Truth and a
judgment of peace you should judge in your gates. So even when
you're talking to the judges you should seek out peace even what
it comes to the judges. והלא במקום שיש משפט אין שלום במקום
שיש שלום אין משפט vehalo bimkom sheyesh mishpat ein shalom bimkom sheyesh
shalom ein mishpat says these are two contradictory. If you're seeking out
justice it's not about finding peace and it's not about making everybody
happy. If you're trying about make everybody happy you're not seeking out
justice. אלא איזהו משפט שיש בו שלום הוי אומר זה ביצוע. ela
eizehu mishpat sheyesh bo shalom hevei omer ze bitzua.
What is the type of a judgment that has peace? That is
compromise. So now it's saying two things. Number one is even when
they come to the judges they can offer and suggest compromise but
also it gets back to the question whether this binding arbitration is
a type of a judgment. Is it one or is it three?
It's a type of a judgment that has in it שלום. shalom.
So there is a sense of applying the law but doing it
with a more flexible approach to context and considerations and all of
that and making a peaceful you know a satisfactory something satisfactory to
all parties but still a version of justice of judgment okay not
just a סתם stam compromise. Okay הוי אומר זה ביצוע hevei omer
ze bitzua וכן בדוד הוא אומר vechein beDovid hu omer by David
it says ויהי דוד עושה משפט וצדקה. vayehi Dovid oseh mishpat u'tzedakah.
David would do משפט וצדקה mishpat u'tzedakah לכל עמו lechol amo to
the end of the פסוק. pasuk. והלא כל מקום שיש משפט אין
צדקה vehalo kol makom sheyesh mishpat ein tzedakah
where there's judgment there's not צדקה. tzedakah. צדקה tzedakah really means righteousness
but here it's using צדקה tzedakah in the more rabbinic sense of
you know charity like helping out people that are poor. Okay you're
the rich guy and really you know you have a right to
kick him out of his apartment and this and that and he'll
go penniless but that would be a משפט mishpat that has no
צדקה. tzedakah. Have a little רחמנות rachmanus on him and let's find
something that actually brings in some other values more than just strict
judgment okay. וכל מקום שיש צדקה אין משפט. vechol makom sheyesh tzedakah
ein mishpat. אלא איזהו משפט שיש בו צדקה. ela eizehu mishpat sheyesh
bo tzedakah.
What's the type of applying justice and judgment that still has an
element of like God you want God to be רחמים בדין rachamim
badin and has an element of צדקה tzedakah in it? So הוי
אומר זה ביצוע. hevei omer ze bitzua. That's ביצוע. bitzua.
So now the גמרא Gemara says אסור לתנא קמא. assur letanna kamma.
Now this actually is going that line is actually going to the
תנא קמא tanna kamma it seems to work well with the idea
that you can suggest ביצוע bitzua even once it comes to you.
But that works when in the earlier discussion when you're talking about
אמת ומשפט שלום. emes umishpat shalom. Here the צדקה tzedakah is not
the way I was interpreting it. I was trying to get it
to all be consistent and reading the צדקה tzedakah as a type
of a sense of like חסד chesed and kindness that comes in
with your judgment. But the גמרא Gemara here is reading צדקה tzedakah
literally sticking your hand in your pocket and giving צדקה. tzedakah. So
the way the גמרא Gemara is reading it that this is actually
going according to the position of אסור לבצוע assur livtzoa and that
what David said what David would do is that David would do
straight justice no compromise but then if the poor person suffered as
a result then David would help stick his hand in his pocket
David would give him צדקה tzedakah in order that it should work
out for him as well. So that was his personal funding of
צדקה tzedakah and it was and it wasn't a you know דין
din that had צדקה tzedakah as a piece of it. So again
I would have rather read that sort of similar to the previous
point about משפט שלום. mishpat shalom. The גמרא Gemara is reading it
in line with the position that it's אסור לבצוע. assur livtzoa. But
we get the idea there are two tracks. One is when they
come to the בית דין beis din all you can do is
דין din and the other is no you can offer them even
when they come to בית דין beis din ביצוע bitzua because that's
a type of a דין ברחמים din berachamim okay that would certainly
work if ביצוע bitzua requires three. Let's keep on going. Okay. דן
את הדין זיכה את הזכאי וחייב את החייב וראה שנתחייב עני ממון
ושילם לו מתוך ביתו זהו משפט צדקה. dan es hadin zikah es
hazakai vechiyav es hachiyav vera'ah shenitchayev ani mamon veshilem lo mitoch beiso
zehu mishpat tzedakah.
Okay so now the גמרא Gemara is saying explicitly the idea that
it is not just that this last point of משפט צדקה mishpat
tzedakah is not like דין ברחמים din berachamim but it's sticking your
hand in your pocket. Okay maybe this is the end of the
ברייתא. braisa. If you made the you know you gave the ruling
and you said the innocent was innocent and the person liable was
liable and what wound up is that the poor person now had
to be out you know all of his money to the rich
person because technically the rich person was right even though that's like
not so fair but that is the justice. Maybe this is the
end of the ברייתא Baraita, *braita*. If you made it, you know,
you gave the ruling, and you said that the innocent was innocent
and the person liable was liable, and what wound up is that
the poor person now had to be out, you know, all of
his money to the rich person because technically the rich person was
right, even though that's like not so fair, but that is the
justice, okay? וראה שנתחייב עני ממון ושילם לו מביתו *vera shenitchayev ani
mamon veshilem lo mibeito* and then you the judge, you want a
good outcome, not just an outcome according to law. So you make
the עני *ani* whole by paying him out of your pocket. זה
משפט וצדקה *ze mishpat utzedaka*. That is both משפט וצדקה *mishpat utzedaka*.
משפט לזה *mishpat laze*, it's judgment for this, you know, for the
case itself and for the rich person who won, וצדקה לזה *utzedaka
laze*, okay? And it's צדקה tzedakah, *tzedaka* for the poor person. משפט
לזה שהחזירו לו ממון *mishpat laze shehcheziru lo mamon*, the rich person
got his money back and he saw justice being done, וצדקה לזה
ששילם לו מתוך ביתו *utzedaka laze sheshilem lo mitoch beito*. Okay, so
with that end of the ברייתא *braita*, then that is not a
type of a רחמים בדין *rachamim bedin*. That is you do the
judgment, and if you want to make it whole, make it whole
out of your pocket. So that is why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says that's the approach of that אסור לבצוע assur livtzoa? *asur livtzoa*.
Okay, and then it quotes again the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* by דוד
*David*. Now, קשיא ליה *kashya leh*, we'll skip the parentheses. קשיא ליה
לרבי *kashya leh le-Rebbi*. האי לכל עמו *hai lechol amo*, לעני מיבעי
ליה *le-ani mibei leh*. But the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says that דוד
*David* was doing משפט וצדקה לכל עמו *mishpat utzedaka lechol amo*, all
his people. But now we're saying that the צדקה *tzedaka* part was
only for the עניים *aniyim* who would lose out, you know, when
the judgment went against them. אלא *ela*, so rather רבי *Rebbi* says
אף על פי שלא שילם מתוך ביתו *af al pi shelo shilem
mitoch beito*, זהו משפט וצדקה *zehu mishpat utzedaka*. משפט לזה וצדקה לזה
*mishpat laze utzedaka laze*. Even if you didn't pay him, it is
judgment and צדקה *tzedaka*. What is the צדקה *tzedaka*, even reading צדקה
*tzedaka* not as righteousness, but as like, you know, charity? Well, let's
see how it reads it. משפט לזה שהחזירו לו ממונו *mishpat laze
shehcheziru lo mamono*, it's a משפט *mishpat* for the, you know, for
the rich person, he got his money back, וצדקה לזה שהוציא גזילה
מתחת ידו *utzedaka laze shehotzi gzeila mitachat yado*, and it's a צדקה
*tzedaka* for the poor person, or not even the poor person, whoever
is the liable party, we no longer have to be rich and
poor. That's the לכל עמו *lechol amo*. But whoever came before דוד
*David*, it wound up being משפט וצדקה *mishpat utzedaka*. The person who
saw justice being done got his money back, and the person who
lost in the judgment, it was also a kindness or a צדקה
*tzedaka* for that person because what the good that was being done
for that person was that he was no longer holding on to
money that was not his, and by giving the money back, you
know, he was actually doing the right thing, and that is a
kindness to him actually, something good you're doing for him, that he
is you're helping him to keep the law and to not hold
on to ill-gotten goods. So I don't exactly get it because the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* now is reading צדקה *tzedaka* more as like righteousness,
which is the פשט *pshat* read, as opposed to before it was
reading it as like charity. But anyway, but what's pushing the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is the לכל עמו *lechol amo*. That before the משפט
*mishpat* was only for the person who won, but the צדקה *tzedaka*
was only in a case if the poor person was the losing
party. And here everybody gets משפט וצדקה *mishpat utzedaka*. Anytime you win
you get your justice, and anytime you lose it's still righteousness for
you because you're doing the right thing. Okay, רבי שמעון בן מנסיא
Rebbe Shimon ben Menasya, אומר *Rebbi Shimon ben Menasya omer*. שנים שבאו
לפניך *shnayim shebau lefanecha*. Okay, but we still have these basic two
approaches about they come to you, are you allowed to suggest ביצוע
*bitzua* or not, and that has partly, are you perverting דין din
*din* or do you see ביצוע *bitzua* as a type of דין
*din*? רבי שמעון בן מנסיא Rebbe Shimon ben Menasya, אומר *Rebbi Shimon
ben Menasya omer*: שנים שבאו לפניך לדין *shnayim shebau lefanecha ladin*, עד
שלא תשמע דבריהם *ad shelo tishma divreihem*, two people come, before you
start hearing, you know, their claims and counter-claims, they just said we
have a suit before you, או משתשמע דבריהם ואי אתה יודע להיכן
הדין נוטה noteh *o mishetishma divreihem ve-ee ata yodea lehachan hadin noteh*,
or you heard their claims and counter-claims, but it's not obvious to
you yet, you'd have to really get into it before you got
a sense of like who would likely come out, you know,
to win this case, so in that case, ואי אתה יודע להיכן
הדין נוטה *ve-ee ata yodea lehachan hadin noteh*, אתה רשאי לומר להם
צאו ובצעו *ata rashai lomar lahem tze'u uvitz'u*. You can tell them,
you know, I would advise you to work out a compromise. Okay,
it's interesting also the different language here. Are you the one that's
being בוצע botze'ah, *botzea*? You know, if it's a type of a
judgment, maybe you are, maybe it's a type of a דין ברחמים
*din berachamim* and you the court is going to operate in your
binding arbitration mode, in your ביצוע *bitzua* mode, or are you offering
to them this alternative? And he sort of seems to say like
as that, then you can sort of, you know, suggest that they
go and work out on their own some compromise. צאו ובצעו *tze'u
uvitz'u*. משתשמע דבריהם ואי אתה יודע להיכן הדין נוטה *mishetishma divreihem ve-ee
ata yodea lehachan hadin noteh*, once you've heard their claims and counter-claims
and you have a sense who's the who's the right party here,
in that case, אי אתה רשאי לומר להם צאו ובצעו *ee ata
rashai lomar lahem tze'u uvitz'u*. In that case, you cannot recommend that
they go to work out some compromise. Why is that?
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* quotes a פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, שנאמר shenemar
*shenemar*, as it says, פוטר מים ראשית מדון poter mayim reishit madon
*poter mayim reshit madon*, if you want to, the way רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* reads this, exempt yourself from water, from the from the debate,
from the judgment, then you could do it ראשית מדון madon. *reshit
madon* at the beginning of the contention, before you've heard their words,
or ולפני התגלע הריב *velifne hitgala hariv*, before... where the debate, the
argument has become exposed and revealed נטוש *nitosh*,
then you can abandon it. קודם שנתגלע הריב אתה יכול לנטשו *Kodam
shenitgala hariv ata yachol lintoshov*, before it's been revealed you can abandon
it. משנתגלע הריב *mishenitgala hariv*, after it's become revealed אי אתה יכול
לנטשו *ee ata yachol lintoshov*, you cannot abandon it. Okay? So this
seems to be a sense not that this is I mean you
could work obviously this in with the idea that it's that ביצוע
*bitzua* is a type of a רחמים בדין *rachamim bedin*, but the
idea that it says that you're telling them you guys go out
and compromise and the word about your נטוש *nitosh*, your abandoning, does
not seem like you are bringing a type a different type of
a justice to this, but you're exempting yourself from it. You're walking
away. You guys figure it out. And you are not able to
walk away once you have become your judgment is already being activated
here because you already are sort of seeing where the judgment lies,
that requires you then to see that through. Okay, so what we
really have here is three opinions. One is
the parties come to you, that means that they're in a court
of justice, they're asking for justice, you're responsible to administer justice. That
was the first opinion. The other is even after they've come to
you, not exactly clear at what stage, who knows, maybe even after
you have a sense which way it is going, you can offer
that you maybe specifically should do this type of a אמת ומשפט
שלום *emet u'mishpat shalom* because maybe it's a type of a רחמים
בדין *rachamim bedin*, it's a certain type of a justice, ביצוע *bitzua*,
okay, but that's the one that you can sort of always maybe
or certainly at a very late stage suggest it. And the other
is sort of sees this would yet is more in line with
the first one, yes you would be abandoning your responsibility of administering
justice, but it's not as soon as they walk in, it's only
when it's clear which way the judgment is leaning. All right, so
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues like this. Okay. So
ריש
לקיש *Reish Lakish* or some say רבי יהושע בן לקיש *Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Lakish*, different גרסאות *girsaot*, אמר amar, שנים שבאו לדין *amar shnayim
shebau l'din*, two people came to judgment. אחד רך ואחד קשה *echad
rach v'echad kasheh*, one is very soft, and the other is very
firm. So different personalities and
you know we're going to have to figure out how that's going
to play out in the court. So עד שלא תשמע דבריהן או
משתשמע דבריהן ואי אתה יודע להיכן הדין נוטה אתה רשאי לומר להם
איני נזקק לכם *ad shelo tishma divreihen o mishetishma divreihen v'ee ata
yodea l'heichan hadin noteh ata rishai lomar lahem eini nizkak lachem*. So
you're concerned about what's going to be because based on how you're
going to judge and is the firm guy going to come after
you and so on. This really gets to difficult issues because the
judge is said לא תגורו lo taguru מפני איש *lo taguru mipnei
ish*, don't be afraid of people, but people are judges are human.
So is there a way that you could recuse yourself from a
case rather than if you are concerned that you won't be able
to deal with the בעלי דין *ba'alei din* that are coming and
the way they will attack you and so on. So what ריש
לקיש *Reish Lakish* says or רבי יהושע בן לוי *Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi* says is בן לקיש *ben Lakish* says is that before you
actually have engaged them או משתשמע דבריהן ואי אתה יודע להיכן הדין
נוטה *o mishetishma divreihen v'ee ata yodea l'heichan hadin noteh* or the
same type of an idea, before you know which way the judgment
is going, in that case אתה רשאי לומר להם איני נזקק לכם
*ata rishai lomar lahem eini nizkak lachem*. You are able to say
look I'm going to recuse myself. Okay same idea that this is
a form of stepping away, so before it was פשרה psharah. *peshara*
was a form of stepping away, here it's just total stepping away
because you don't want to get in trouble, and until you have
a sense where it's going, you are not yet considered to be
compromising your integrity perverting justice and you're allowed to step away. איני
נזקק לכם שמא נתחייב חזק ונמצא חזק רודפו *eini nizkak lachem shema
nitchayev chazak v'nimtza chazak rodfo* because you're afraid that the one who
is the firm guy is going to be found guilty and he's
going to come and chase after you. משתשמע דבריהן ואתה יודע להיכן
הדין נוטה *mishetishma divreihen v'ata yodea l'heichan hadin noteh* but once you
have a sense which way the judgment is going then that locks
you in. Now you are responsible to see it through. You cannot
step away now that would be a perversion of justice and of
your obligation. אי אתה רשאי לומר להם איני נזקק לכם *ee ata
rishai lomar lahem eini nizkak lachem* at that stage you cannot say
I'm no longer dealing with this, שנאמר shene'emar *shene'emar* and this is
exactly what the פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* is about לא תגורו lo taguru?
מפני איש *lo taguru mipnei ish*, do not be afraid of any
man כי המשפט לאלוקים הוא *ki hamishpat l'elokim hu* you're doing God's
justice. So actually it's clear that a פסוק pasuk? *Pasuk* says you
can't step away and you can't be afraid. The חידוש *chidush* here
is it allows you to step away at earlier stages. רבי יהושע
בן קרחה Rebbe Yehoshua ben Korcha אומר *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha omer*,
רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rebbe Yehoshua ben Korcha *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha*
says מניין לתלמיד שיושב לפני רבו וראה זכות לעני וחובה לעשיר מניין
שלא ישתוק *minayin l'talmid sheyoshev lifnei rabo v'ra'ah z'chut l'ani v'chova l'ashir
minayin shelo yishtok* how do you know if somebody is there and
they're like a clerk, they're sitting in front of their רבי *Rebbe*
but they're listening to the court case and they see that
actually that there's merit for the poor person something could be argued
in his defense or something bad for the rich person I mean
it really could go the other way too, but how he sees
something
that and he needs to speak up, he wants justice to be
done, מניין שלא ישתוק *minayin shelo yishtok*, how do you know that
he cannot be silent? שנאמר לא תגורו מפני איש *shene'emar lo taguru
mipnei ish*, do not be afraid of any person but here תגורו
*taguru* is read as. as like אגור *agor* to gather in your
words, you know you have a responsibility to share them and not
be afraid. So don't be afraid of your רבי *Rebbi*, and don't
even be afraid of the rich person. I mean that's presumably why
it's framed that way. You have a responsibility to justice and to
speak up. רבי חנינא *Rebbi Chanina* אומר *omer* לא תכניס דבריך מפני
איש *lo tachnis devarecha mipnei ish*. This is presumably the point. Don't
hold your work back because of somebody even if you're not the
judge and you're just sitting there and observing the case. So that
creates an even greater responsibility, I mean more greater in the sense
of more than we would have imagined in terms of who's responsible.
והיו עדים יודעים את מי הם מעידים ולפני מי הם מעידים ומי
עתיד להיפרע מהם *V'hayu edim yod'im et mi hem mei'idim v'lifnei mi
hem mei'idim u'mi atid lipara mehem*. And now a slightly different point,
the witnesses should be aware of who are they judging and before
who they're testifying and who is going to you know exact from
them. So before whom is God, who's going to exact from them
is God. But now we're going to find out even מי הם
מעידים *mi hem mei'idim*, who are they testifying against to some degree
is also God, right? So now the same way you have all
this heavy responsibility on the judges to see through the truth, heavy
responsibility on the witnesses. Okay, שנאמר *shene'emar* is the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
says, ועמדו שני האנשים אשר להם הריב לפני השם *v'amdu shnei ha'anashim
asher lahem hariv lifnei Hashem*, the two people that have the judgment
and this is read not to be referring to the litigants but
for the עדים *edim* should stand before God. They are presenting themselves
before God. Okay, and okay and if you look at רש''י Rashi
*Rashi* at מי הם מעידים *mi hem mei'idim*, רש''י Rashi *Rashi* says
against who are they testifying, כאילו הן מעידים בהקדוש ברוך הוא שמטריחין
אותו להחזיר ממון לבעלו *ke'ilu hen mei'idim b'Hakadosh Baruch Hu she'matrichin oto
lehachazir mamon l'ba'alo*. Because if they testify falsely, God will have
to administer the justice and not the court. So your false testimony
is it can can impact like you know you're making God have
to work harder and God has to go ahead and make this
person get his money back. So it's like you're testifying against God
and you're perverting God's you know the justice that's applying to God.
Okay, okay. והיו הדיינין יודעים את מי הן דנין ולפני מי הן
דנין ומי עתיד להיפרע מהם *V'hayu hadayanin yod'im et mi hen danin
v'lifnei mi hen danin u'mi atid lipara mehem*. And similarly the judges
have to know who are they judging you know in front of
who are they judging and who will pay them back? שנאמר *Shene'emar*,
אלקים נצב בעדת אל *Elokim nitzav ba'adat El*, God stands in the
congregation of God which is understood that God is present there among
the judges. וכן ביהושפט הוא אומר *v'chen bi'Yehoshaphat hu omer* וכי הוה
אתו לקמיה דרב הונא *Ve'ki hava atu l'kamei d'Rav Huna* and he
said to the judges, ויאמר לשופטים *vayomer lashoftim* and he said to
the judges, ראו מה אתם עושים כי לא לאדם תשפטו כי להשם
*r'u mah atem osim ki lo l'adam tishpotu ki l'Hashem*, see what
you are doing because not for man do you judge but for
God. You're instilling God's justice but also to some degree you're impacting
God by perverting justice. שמא יאמר דיין מה לי בצער זה *Shema
yomar dayan mah li b'tzar zeh*, lest the judge says why do
I need this all of this anguish? Like this is too much
responsibility, I'm just checking out. So תלמוד לומר *talmud lomar*, עמכם בדבר
משפט *imachem bidvar mishpat*, that God is with you in the matter
of justice. Meaning not just saying it's too much responsibility but oh
my God, if I get something wrong, I'm all going to have
to pay, I can't deal with it like I'll be terrified that
I'm going to פסקן *pasken* incorrectly. No, God is with you. אין
לו לדיין אלא מה שעיניו רואות *Ein lo l'dayan ela mah she'einav
ro'ot*, that if you deal with integrity then you nobody expects you
to be a superhero and you can only judge as much as
best as you can assess the situation. So as long as you
do it with honesty and integrity and with rigor and so on,
then God is with you and you do not have to fear
for you know making mistakes. Okay and therefore not to withhold yourself.
רב משה פיינשטיין *Rav Moshe Feinstein* talks about that as פסק psak
הלכה *psak halacha*. If you go through the process with integrity, whatever
you come up with will be legitimate הלכה *halacha*. You know that's
like the idea of לא בשמים היא *lo bashamayim hi*. Not exactly
this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s point but like you can understand the trepidation
of responsibility. Okay, היכי דמי גמר דין gmar din, *heichi dami gmar
din*? Now back to the earlier point that once there's גמר דין
gmar din *gmar din*, you know you cannot be בוצע botze'ah. *botzei'a*,
that's according to everybody. You know there were different opinions once they
came in front of you, once you know להיכן הדין נוטה *leheichan
hadin noteh*, at what stage maybe you should not be בוצע *botzei'a*,
but it certainly is not allowed once there's גמר דין gmar din,
*gmar din*. So what's גמר דין gmar din. *gmar din*? אמר amar,
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda. אמר רב *Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav*, איש
פלוני אתה חייב איש פלוני אתה זכאי *ish ploni atah chayav איש
פלוני אתה זכאי *ish ploni atah zakai*. When they say you're liable
or you're exempt, that is גמר דין *gmar din*. Pretty clear that
after that, I mean I don't know who'd be stupid enough to
agree to a פשרה psharah, *pshara* at that point. But anyway, אמר
רב *Amar Rav*, הלכה כרבי יהושע בן קרחה *halacha k'Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Korcha*. We rule like רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rebbe Yehoshua ben Korcha
*Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha*, who was the one who said it's a
מצוה לבצוע mitzvah livtzoa, *mitzvah livtzo'a* and called it משפט שלום *mishpat
shalom*. Okay, so איני *eini*, is this really true? והא רב הונא
תלמידיה דרב הוה *Ve'ha Rav Huna talmidei d'Rav havah*. רב הונא *Rav
Huna* was a student of רב *Rav*, so presumably followed the ruling
here of רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rebbe Yehoshua ben Korcha *Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Korcha*. וכי הוה אתו לקמיה דרב הונא *Ve'ki hava atu l'kamei
d'Rav Huna*, and when he came to רב הונא *Rav Huna* and
when litigants came to רב הונא *Rav Huna*, אמר להו *amar lehu*,
he would say to them, אי דינא בעיתו או פשרה psharah, בעיתו
*idina ba'itu o pshara ba'itu*. What do you want? Do you want
me to deal with you should it be a normal case, you
know normal according to the law, justice or do you want פשרה
psharah, *pshara* compromise? And according to רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rebbe Yehoshua
ben Korcha *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha* presumably it's a מצוה mitzvah לבצוע
*mitzvah livtzo'a*, so you should actually be encouraging them. Right? Do you
lay out all the options or do you try to Point them
in one direction? So the גמרא Gemara, says no, מאי מצוה נמי
דקאמר רבי יהושע בן קרחה, mai mitzvah nami dikamar Rebbe Yehoshua ben
Korcha, top of ז' עמוד א', zayin amud alef, מצוה למימר להו
אי דינא בעיתו פשר בעיתו. mitzvah lemeimar lehu i dina ba'itu pshar
ba'itu. It doesn't mean that you're supposed to encourage them specifically to
pick it, but you are supposed to lay it out as an
equal, as an equal offering. Okay. So you have the first opinions,
you know, that would have said like once they come in front
of you, it's forbidden for you to go down that path. Once
or, you know, a slightly lighter version of that, once you know
where it's heading, it's forbidden for you to go down that path.
And רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rebbe Yehoshua ben Korcha says no, even
when they come down to you, there's a value in being בוצע,
but as opposed to saying you should push it and encourage it,
he's saying you should lay it out as an equal and equal
possibility.
All right.
So the גמרא Gemara says היינו תנא קמא? hainu tanna kamma? But
wait, once you're just saying that you can offer it, how is
that different than the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma who says אסור לבצוע?
assur livtzoa. So the גמרא Gemara says no, איכא בינייהו מצוה. ika
beinaihu mitzvah. That this is exactly the difference that
not the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that said אסור assur. לבצוע. Obviously,
this is different than אסור. assur, This is saying it's מותר, mutar,
you can lay it out. But how is this different than the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma who said once it's גמר דין, you can't
be בוצע. From that, it sounds like beforehand it's an option. So
if the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma was saying before גמר דין it's
an option and רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rebbe Yehoshua ben Korcha: is
saying it's an option, aren't they saying the same thing? So the
גמרא Gemara says no, איכא בינייהו מצוה. ika beinaihu mitzvah. So no,
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma said it's not forbidden, but he's not
interested in you suggesting it. If they ask for it, you can
do it. Whereas רבי יהושע בן קרחה says no, you actually should
suggest it. So the גמרא Gemara stepped away from the idea possibility
that you should actively promote it, but we still have the פסק
psak of רבי יהושע בן קרחה that says even when they come
to you, maybe even after you've heard them, maybe who knows, maybe
even after you know היכא הדין נוטה, heicha hadin noteh, but certainly
anyway at an earlier stage it's a מצוה mitzvah, to let them
know that this is an option, whereas the other opinions are like:
No, at a certain stage it's אסור, assur, once they come, once
you know היכא הדין נוטה, heicha hadin noteh, and maybe even at
an earlier stage, even if it's not אסור, you shouldn't be mentioning
it. If they suggest it, you can go down that path. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: So איכא בינייהו מצוה.
ika beinaihu mitzvah. רבי יהושע בן קרחה סבר savar מצוה, תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma סבר רשות. savar reshut. So the גמרא Gemara says היינו
דרבי שמעון בן מנסיא? hainu de-Rebbe Shimon ben Menasya? One minute, says
the גמרא, that if the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is
saying that you know if they raise it you can go down
that path then and but only but not after there's גמר דין,
isn't that what רבי יהושע בן קרחה said? He said that you
know once you know where the דין is נוטה you can't go
down the path. So no, there's a difference. איכא בינייהו משתשמע דבריהם
ואתה יודע להיכן הדין נוטה אי אתה רשאי לומר להם צאו ובצעו.
ika beinaihu mishetishma divreihem ve'atah yode'a leheichan hadin noteh ee attah rashai
lomar lahem tze'u uvitz'u.
The question is that you know that at what point is it
no longer allowed to be saying it? For the תנא קמא, Tanna
Kamma, even if you know where it's going, you know up up
to the moment you say you give the פסק דין, psak din,
you can allow them to go ahead and do a פשרה. According
to רבי שמעון בן מנסיא, you're not allowed to once you know
היכא הדין נוטה. heicha hadin noteh. So to review, you have the
פסק of who was it of רבי יהושע בן קרחה: מצוה לבצוע,
which means even after they come to you and even maybe well
into the whole judgment and who knows, you should be let them
know, proactively let them know that this is an option. Maybe don't
דווקא davka encourage it, but proactively let them know that this is
an option. According to all the other opinions, keep your mouth shut,
don't let them know about it. If they suggest it, then there's
a debate. You know, there was the one opinion that said רבי
אלעזר בנו של רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbe Elazar beno shel Rebbe Yose
HaGlili that even if they suggest it, you are not allowed to
go down that path once they come in front of you in
the court. You know, you've got the תנא Tanna you've got רבי
שמעון בן מנסיא, excuse me, who says you can go down that
path until you know היכא הדין נוטה heicha hadin noteh and the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that you can go down that path until
it is actually גמר דין. All right. Now ופליגא דרבי תנחום בר
חנילאי. upliga de-Rebbe Tanchum bar Chanilai. This argues on רבי תנחום בר
חנילאי. Rebbe Tanchum bar Chanilai. דאמר רבי תנחום בר חנילאי: de'amar Rebbe
Tanchum bar Chanilai: לא נאמר מקרא זה אלא כנגד מעשה העגל. lo
ne'emar mikra zeh ela keneged ma'aseh ha'eigel.
This פסוק pasuk. about בוצע ברך, botze'ah berech, you know the way
we were using it for like about פשרה, he says that was
not said about פשרה, it was said about the חטא העגל cheit
ha'eigel where אהרן Aharon made a compromise. Okay. And so let's take
a look. If you look at רש"י last of the wide lines
of רש"י at the top: אלא כנגד מעשה העגל שעשה אהרן פשרה
בינו לבין עצמו והורה היתר לעצמו לעשות להם העגל. ela keneged ma'aseh
ha'eigel she'asah Aharon pshara beino levein atzmo vehoreh heter le'atzmo la'asot lahem
ha'eigel.
He compromised with his own conscience and integrity and came up with
this, you know, with this approach.
Okay, with so שנאמר as the פסוק pasuk. says: וירא אהרן ויבן
מזבח לפניו. vayar Aharon vayiven mizbe'ach lefanav. מה ראה אהרן? mah ra'ah
Aharon? So ready build He understood מזבוח
לפניו mi zavuach lefanav from the one who had been slaughtered in
his presence. He understood that he could not stand up to them
or he was going to die. So he had to come up
with some type of a reasonable פשרה, reasonable thing to maybe dissuade
them but not to directly confront them. You know, that's always the
question. It gets back to the story before about יהודה, Yehuda, about
ראובן, Reuven, what ראובן Reuven did to try to save יוסף Yosef
about half measures, you know, if you try to go the whole
distance you're going to get yourself killed and not accomplish anything. But
the גמרא here is not having any of it. Okay, אמר, so
אמר רבי אלעזר: amar Rabbi Elazar: ראה חור שזבוח לפניו. ra'ah chur
shezavuach lefanav. He saw חור Chur that was slaughtered and אמר, he
said: אילו שמענא להו השתא ilo shamana lehu hashta עבדו לי כדעבדו
בחור. avdu li kide’avdu beChur.
If I don't listen to them and build the עגל, egel, they'll
do to me like they did to חור Chur now. That could
just be self-preservation, I don't want to get killed, you know, but
the גמרא is making it a little bit more than just self-preservation.
ומקיים בי umekayem bi אם יהרג במקדש ה' כהן ונביא. im yehareg
bemikdash Hashem kohen venavi.
That פסוק pasuk. which hasn't been said yet, you know, but that's
like oh my god, the imagine the blasphemy, the tragedy that slaughtered
a כהן kohen and נביא navi in the מקדש. mikdash. I'll be
the כהן kohen and נביא. navi. There wasn't a מקדש mikdash yet,
but okay. ולא הוי להו תקנתא לעולם. velo havi lehu takanah le'olam.
And then, you know, once they killed חור, Chur, but if they
kill me, it'll be so horrific that they'll never be forgiven. So
מוטב דיעבדו לעגל. mutav deya'avdu la'egel. It's better that they should do
the עגל. egel. אפשר הוי להו תקנתא בתשובה. efshar havi lehu takanah
betshuvah.
I'll make them the עגל egel and maybe and then we can
do תשובה. tshuvah. It's עבודה זרה avodah zarah but it's not this
thing that is so horrific. It's interesting. That would be more horrific
than עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. It's also more horrific that it's אהרן
Aharon then it's חור Chur anyway. Okay, so it's interesting. Now maybe
that was his own compromise, right? Maybe that was his own מורה
היתר. moreh heter. Maybe he really was motivated by self-preservation, but he
was telling himself that he was doing it in order to, you
know, to save them from an even more grievous sin. והני תנאי
פוטר מים ראשית מדון מדרשי ביה. vehanai tana'ei poter mayim reishit madon
madreshei beih. And the other תנאים Tana'im that say that you are
don't read this פסוק pasuk of פוטר מים ראשית מדון poter mayim
reishit madon. that at a certain stage you're allowed to exempt yourself,
at a later stage you're not allowed to walk off, what do
they do with the פסוק? pasuk. So כדרב המנונא. kedrav Hamnuna. Like
רב המנונא. Rav Hamnuna. דאמר רב המנונא: damar Rav Hamnuna: אין תחלת
דינו של אדם נידון אלא על דברי תורה. ein techilat dino shel
adam nadon ela al divrei Torah. A person is first judged in
terms of, you know, his תורה. Torah. If he was מבטל mevatel
from תורה. Torah. Rashi says if he was מבטל mevatel from תורה.
Torah. שנאמר as the פסוק pasuk says פוטר מים ראשית מדון. poter
mayim reishit madon. If you exempt yourself from מים, mayim, תורה Torah
is compared to water. הוי כל צמא לכו למים. hoy kol tzamei
lechu lamayim. That is the first that thing you will be judged
on. אמר רב הונא: amar Rav Huna: האי תיגרא דמיא לצינורא דבידקא
דמיא. hai tigra damya letzinora debitka damya. So this you know,
excuse me, I think I read that wrong. One is דמיא, demaiya,
one is דמיא. damya. So האי תיגרא דמיא. hai tigra damya. So
a fight, what is it comparable to? לצינורא
דבידקא דמיא. letzinora debitka damya. To like a hose that has a
the, you know, that has a crack in the hose. כיון דרווח
רווח. keivan deravach ravach. That, you know, once it gets wide it
gets wide. So if you have a crack in the hose, it'll
just expand and expand. So similarly if you have a fight, you
need to try to heal it right away or just it's going
to get deeper and deeper.
אביי קשישא אמר: Abaye kishisha amar: דמי לגודא דגמלא. dami leguda degamla.
It's similar to a like a
board
of a bridge. כיון דקם קם. keivan dekam kam. That once it's
like been, you know, established stable, then it's going to be firm.
So, you know, once a fight gets deep in, good luck trying
to, you know, to get people to reconcile. Okay, so now the
גמרא continues. It's got these ראשי תיבות rashei teivot as a just
way of remembering it from an oral tradition. ההוא דהוה קאמר. hahu
dehavah ka'amar. There was a person who used to say ואזיל. ve'azil.
He was going and he was saying: טוביה דשמע ואדיש. tuvya deshama
ve'adish.
It is good to somebody who hears insults and bad things being
said to him and he basically, you know, ignores it or remains
silent. חפו ביה מאה בישתא. chafu beih me'ah bishta. You know, a
hundred misfortunes, bad things will not happen to him as a result.
Just let it all wash off of you. אמר ליה שמואל לרב
יהודה. amar leih Shmuel leRav Yehuda. So שמואל Shmuel said to רב
יהודה. Rav Yehuda, קרא כתיב. kra ktiv.
It's a פסוק. pasuk. פוטר מים poteir mayim, ראשית מדון. madon The
one who releases water it's the first of מדון. madon ריש מאה
דיני. reish me'ah dinei. So reading מדון as the beginning of a
hundred litigations, a hundred judgments. So if you release strife, the beginning
of strife, you know, that's what the simple sense means is that
it brings out a hundred judgments. So if you just let it
go then you free yourself from all of those bad things. רש"י
also points out that the word מדון in גימטריא gematria is a
hundred. It's also מאה דיני. me'ah dinei. A hundred judgments. הוא דהוה
קאמר ואזיל, Hu d'havah ka'amar ve'azil, somebody was going and saying, אטרתי
תלת גן ולא מטל, Atarti tlas gan v'lo mital, that, you know,
and he was saying that that
like
somebody is not killed, you know, by God for two or three
thefts, meaning as רש״י Rashi says, you know, somebody does an עבירה
aveirah two times, three times, nothing's happened to me, you know, you
think okay, that's it, like you're going to get away with it,
God's going to, God won't punish you or something like that. So
he was saying, you know, two or three times it won't happen,
but eventually you'll get your judgment.
So אמר ליה שמואל לרב יהודה, Amar lei Shmuel l'Rav Yehuda, so
שמואל Shmuel said to רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, קרא כתיב, kra ksiv,
it's in a פסוק. pasuk. כה אמר השם על שלשה פשעי אדם
ועל ארבעה לא אשיבנו, Koh amar Hashem al shlosha pishei Adam v'al
arba'a lo ashivenu, on three and in four of the sins, ישראל,
Yisrael, excuse me, on four I will not, you know, pay them
back, but more than that, you know, once it gets to be
enough, they'll get their payment back. So it's interesting, obviously we're starting
this discussion because of פוטר מים, but we're trying to find ways
in which like common aphorisms are already in the פסוקים. psukim. הוא
דהוה קאמר ואזיל, Hu d'havah ka'amar ve'azil, somebody was going and saying,
שב בירי לשלמנא וחדא לעביד ביש, Shav biri l'shalmana v'chada l'avid bish,
that there can be seven pits for somebody who is a man
of, you know, somebody who's like a good person, a man of
peace, and he'll avoid all of the traps, but for a bad
person, they'll fall into just one pit. You know, if only life
worked that way. אמר ליה שמואל לרב יהודה, Amar lei Shmuel l'Rav
Yehuda, so שמואל Shmuel said to רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, קרא כתיב,
kra ksiv, it's a פסוק. pasuk. כי שבע יפול צדיק וקם, Ki
sheva yipol tzaddik v'kam, that a, the righteous will fall seven times
and get up, so even if there are things that are made
there to make him stumble, in the end he will survive them.
And the פסוק pasuk we, and the גמרא we have says, ורשעים
יפלו באחת, u'resha'im yipolu b'achas, you know, and a wicked person will
fall in one, but that's not actually the פסוק. pasuk. On the
פסוק pasuk you see it says in the side,
ורשעים יכשלו ברעה. u'resha'im yikashlu b'ra'ah. Alright, but anyway, so but the
wicked will
stumble, so even a small thing, somebody who's wicked will not recover.
Again, if only the world worked that way. Okay. הוא דהוה קאמר
ואזיל, Hu d'havah ka'amar ve'azil, somebody was going and saying, דאזיל מבי
דינא שקיל גלימא ליזמר זמר וליזיל, De'azil mi'bei dina shakil glima lizmar
zemar v'leizil, that, you know, somebody goes from the court and his
garment was taken from him, you know, he should be sing a
song and going happy on his way, באורחא וליזיל באורחא, b'orcha v'leizil
b'orcha, because because, you know, because ultimately he's now no longer holding
on to stolen goods. It's like the גמרא before about צדקה, you
let him to be righteous. So אמר ליה שמואל לרב יהודה, Amar
lei Shmuel l'Rav Yehuda, שמואל Shmuel said to רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda,
קרא כתיב, kra ksiv, it's a פסוק. וגם כל העם הזה על
מקומו יבא בשלום, V'gam kol ha'am hazeh al mekomo yavo v'shalom, this
entire people will go to peace if you have good judgment, even
the ones that are found guilty, it'll be peace for everyone. הוא
דהוה קאמר ואזיל, Hu d'havah ka'amar ve'azil, somebody was going and saying,
היי נאמה ודיקולא שפיל. Hai namma v'dikulla shapil. So if like
if a, if somebody is carrying, a woman is carrying like a
basket on her head, if she's dozing off, ודיקולא שפיל, v'dikulla shapil,
the basket will fall down. Okay, like if, you know, if you're
somebody is nodding off, like what is it, lazy hands, no, that's
idle hands is the devil's playground, but okay, inattention will lead to
bad things happening. אמר ליה שמואל לרב יהודה, Amar lei Shmuel l'Rav
Yehuda, so שמואל Shmuel said to רב יהודה, האי קרא כתיב, hai
kra ksiv, it's a פסוק. בעצלתים ימך המקרה, Ba'atzaltayim yemach hamikreh, that
with, you know, in by laziness the rafters will, will warp, will
sink in. Okay. הוא דהוה קאמר ואזיל, Hu d'havah ka'amar ve'azil, somebody
was going and saying, גברא דרחיצנא עליה אדיא לי גזיזיה, Gavra d'rachitzna
alei adya li gzizeih, that the person that I, you know, that
I, that I was relied upon
lifted his fist against me, וקם, v'kam, and you know, and got
up. So, you know, so he rose up against me, so I
was betrayed. So אמר ליה שמואל לרב יהודה, Amar lei Shmuel l'Rav
Yehuda, קרא כתיב, kra ksiv, it's a פסוק. וגם כי איש שלומי
אשר בטחתי בו, V'gam ki ish shlomi asher batachti vo, the person
of my, you know, of my faith that I had put my
confidence in, you know, that person basically has,
the end of the פסוק is, ate my bread and lifted up,
you know, lifted his foot against me. So alright, so people sometimes,
you know, you trust somebody and they will betray your trust. I'm
not exactly sure what the point of that aphorism is. הוא דהוה
קאמר ואזיל, Hu d'havah ka'amar ve'azil, somebody was going and saying,
כי רחימתין הוי עזיזא אפותיא דספסירא שכיבן, Ki rechimtin havai aziza a'putya
d'safsira shchivan, when our love was strong we would be able to
sleep on a bed like by like on the edge of a
sword. We could have, you know, when in the good old days
when we were just married and we were, you know, we lived
in this tiny little hovel and everything was everything was amazing. Okay.
You know, could have been very, really living in straits but our
love kept us going. השתא דלא עזיזא רחימתין, Hashta d'lo aziza rechimtin,
now that our love is not strong, פוריא בר שיתין גרמידא לא
סגי לן, purya bar shitin garmida lo sagi lan, even a bed
of sixty אמות, amot, you know, we have this nice luxurious house
and we can't stand each other and it just things are miserable.
So so it really is the love that makes the difference, not
the, you know, not the physical and the material issues. So אמר
רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, קראי כתיבי, krai ksivi, it's a פסוק.
מעיקרא כתיב ונועדתי לך שם ודברתי אתך מעל הכפרת, Me'ikara ksiv v'noadeti
lecha sham v'dibarti itcha me'al hakaporet, originally God said I will speak
to you from above the ark, meaning that the שכינה Shechinah came
down and the ark was ten טפחים tefachim off of the ground.
down and was right there with us, like right in the
ten טפחים tefachim right before the space that was for the human
beings, God's presence
was confined and right in that little space. Okay, that's what it
originally was. And then we turn to the ברייתא, ארון תשעה וכפורת
טפח הרי כאן עשרה. Aron tish'a ve'kapporet tefach harei kan asara. The
ארון Aron was nine טפחים, tefachim, the כפורת kapporet a טפח, tefach,
that's ten טפחים. tefachim. God was right there within ten טפחים tefachim
of the ground, so close to us. וכתיב, ve'ketiv, but then later
it says והבית אשר בנה שלמה להשם ששים אמה ארכו. vehabayit asher
bana Shlomo la'Hashem shishim ama orko. The second the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash that שלמה Shlomo built sixty אמות amot wide ועשרים רחבו ושלשים
אמה קומתו, ve'esrim rochvo u'shloshim ama komato, thirty אמות amot tall. You
have this huge ושלשים אמות u'shloshim amot and לסוף כתיב u'lesof ketiv
and then when we sinned it says כה אמר השם השמים כסאי
והארץ הדם רגלי אי זה בית אשר תבנו לי. koh amar Hashem
hashamayim kisi veha'aretz hadom raglai eizeh bayit asher tivnu li. What house
will you make for me? Meaning I'm leaving this house, I can't
dwell with you anymore. So God not only couldn't be squeezed down
to the עשר אמות, eser amot, ten טפחים, tefachim, he couldn't even
be in a house that had thirty אמות amot high, he had
to leave the whole house.
Okay, מאי משמע דהאי לא תגורו, mai mashma dehai lo taguru, now
just wrapping up, where do you get this idea that לא תגורו
לישנא דכינושי הוא? lishana dekinnushei hu? When it says you can't hold
your words back if you see that the judgment belongs like you
see that something needs to be said in the court and the
גמרא said even if you're a student don't hold your words back.
Where do you see that's the word לא תגורו? אמר רב נחמן
אמר קרא, Amar Rav Nachman amar kra, the פסוק says ויין לא
תשתה ולא תאגר. veyayin lo tishteh velo te'egor. Wine you won't drink
and you won't gather in. So it means to gather in. רב
אחא בר יעקב אמר מהכא, Rav Acha bar Yaakov amar meihacha, תכין
בקיץ לחמה, tachin bakayitz lachma, it prepares in, this is about like
the industrious ant, prepares in the summer its bread, אגרה בקציר מאכלה,
agra bakatzir ma'achala, gathers up in the harvest season its food. רב
אחא בריה דרב איקא אמר מהכא, Rav Acha brei deRav Ika amar
meihacha, אוגר בקיץ בן משכיל. oger bakayitz ben maskil.
That in the summer a wise son will gather. So אוגר oger
means to gather up. Okay, we will end here.